NYSUT Public Relations Department Files. 6174/006
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
NYSUT Public Relations Department Files
1983-1998
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT)
6174/006
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Reports, pamphlets, correspondence.
7164240
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183> kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, June 13, 2012
EAD encoding:
Randall Miles, October 31, 2013
Biographical / Historical
New York State United Teachers (NYSUT) was created in 1972 by the merger of the New York State Teachers Association (NYSTA) and the United Teachers of New York (UTNY). NYSTA had been affiliated with the National Education Association (NEA), and UTNY with the American Federation of Teachers (AFT). UTNY was the statewide organization whose United Federation of Teachers (UFT), led by Albert Shanker, was the predominant teachers' union in New York City. In joining with United Teachers and affiliating with the AFT, NYSUT also became a member union of the AFL-CIO.
In 1976, NYSUT voted to disaffiliate with the NEA. Some locals left NYSUT and created the NYEA (New York Educators Association), which became the state affiliate for the NEA. In the early 1980s, NYEA changed its name to NEA-NY.
NYEA/NEA- NY viewed association with the AFL-CIO's industrial unions as undermining the professional image and independence of teachers. The two organizations also differed strongly on aspects of the governance structure, particularly with respect to ethnic minority representation, with NYSUT opposed to mandatory minimums. The rivalry between NYSUT and NYEA/NEA-NY in organizing new locals expended a great deal of resources for both labor organizations.
While competition with NYEA/NEA-NY was a constant focus of NYSUT's organizing efforts for teachers, NYSUT was also organizing college faculty members, nurses, and other non-teaching personnel. Once members were organized, NYSUT continued to advocate for teachers' and other workers' rights through contract support and legal services at the local level and political involvement at the state and federal levels, supporting candidates and legislation that protected funding, due process, and working conditions.
NEA-N Y merged with NYSUT in 2006, by which time NYSUT had grown to more than half a million members, becoming the largest union in New York State.
Biographical / Historical
The Public Relations Department produced public service announcements and the cable video show "Inside Your Schools," highlighting educational issues. It also produced the newsletter for local leaders, Bottom Line.
Scope and Contents
Covers Public Relations Department files 1983-1998. Final print copies of Bottom Line newsletter for local leaders, and background production materials; production worksheets for public service announcements and video segments for "Inside Your Schools" cable series addressing educational issues such as teacher shortage
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: All other 6174 collections
Teachers' union, New York (State); Allen, Steve; Alsop, Lamar; Blatnick, Jeff; Dunn, Walter; Fitzgerald, Brian; Haley, Alex; Shanker, Albert; New York State United Teachers. Archives; New York State United Teachers, Public Relations Department
7164240
- Summary of Proceedings, 1985-1991 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Daily summaries of annual Representative Assembly conventions
- Bottom Line-Vol. 1, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Jan.-June. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 2, 1983-1984 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Sept. 1983-June 1984. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 3, 1984-1985 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Aug.1984-June 1985. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 4, 1985-1986 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Aug. 1985- June 1986. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 5, 1986-1987 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Aug. 1986-June 1987. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 6, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Aug. 28, 1987-June 24, 1988. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 7, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Sept. 1, 1988-June 16, 1989. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 8, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Aug. 31, 1989-June 22, 1990. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 9, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Aug. 30, 1990-June 21, 1991. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 10, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Aug. 29,1991-June 19, 1992. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 11, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Sept. 4, 1992-June 18, 1993. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 12, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Sept. 3, 1993-June 17, 1994. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 13, 1994-1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Sept. 2, 1994-June 9, 1995. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 14 (1 of 2), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Sept. 1-Dec. 8. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 14 (2 of 2), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Jan 5, 1996-June 7, 1996. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 15 (1 of 2), 1996 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Aug. 30, 1996-Nov. 22, 1996. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 15 (2 of 2), 1996-1997 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Dec. 6, 1996-June 13, 1997. Newsletters for NYSUT local leaders
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 1, 1997 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Sept. 5, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 2, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Sept. 19,1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 3, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Oct. 3, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 4, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Oct. 17, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 5, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Oct. 31, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 6, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Nov. 14, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 7, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Nov. 28, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 8, 1997 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Dec. 12, 1997. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 9, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Jan. 16, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 10, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Jan. 30,1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 11, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Feb. 13, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 12, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Feb. 27, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 13, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  March 13, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 14, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  March 27, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 15, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  April 10, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 16, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  April 24, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 17, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  May 8, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 18, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  May 22, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 20, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  June 19, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- Bottom Line-Vol. 16, No. 19, 1998 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  June 5, 1998. Newsletter for NYSUT local leaders (printed copy); drafts of articles; newspaper clippings and other background materials
- SADD Notes-State of Education (S.O.E.), 1984-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Letter to NYSUT director of public relations Peter Bloespflug from founder of Students Against Drunk Driving, January 3, 1984; flyer, "A Parent's Guide to Teenage Parties"; letter to NYSUT president Tom Hobart from NYS Council on Alcoholism, requesting copy of NYSUT-produced video, January 22, 1985; letter to NYSUT Public Relations Department from NYS Division of Substance Abuse Services, with attached list of contacts in counties with peer leadership programs, December 18, 1984; newspaper clippings
- SADD-411 Paperwork-Tape 518-98M, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Students Against Drunk Driving publications, "If we dream it, it can be done," and "SADD Handbook and Curriculum Guide," 1983; scripts for NYSUT audio spots, "Inside Your Schools"; scripts for video segments
- State of Education (S.O.E.) Year of the Teacher Tape 508-98M, 1985 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  March. State of Education video production scripts
- Children's Suite-Paperwork-Tapes: 410-20R, 410-24R, 410-29 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  Video production scripts
- Children's Suite-410 Paperwork (Box 2, Folder 24)
  Audio script; video production scripts; music scores
- Children's Suite (folder 2) (Box 3, Folder 1)
- State of Education Professionalization-Tape 522-98M, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  Interview transcript with Watertown superintendent; video production worksheets; notes from governor's news conference
- Watertown 550 Teleconference (Box 3, Folder 3)
  Transcript of interviews with teachers
- Educational Conferences-Tape 513-98M State of Education, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  April. Video production worksheets; conference program; participant evaluation form
- Epidemic 450 Tapes 450-3, 450-06, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  Drug-awareness flyers by NYS Division of Substance Abuse Services and Citizens Alliance to Prevent Drug Abuse; video production worksheets; audio scripts; correspondence re legal (ownership) status of video "Epidemic: America Fights Back"
- Epidemic 450 Pamphlets (1 of 2), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  Booklets by Citizens Alliance to Prevent Drug Abuse and NYS Division of Substance Abuse Services, "Handbook for Parents," including contacts by county, May; "Substance Abuse Prevention Resources," October
- Epidemic 450 Pamphlets (2 of 2), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  NYS Division for Youth "Masterplan 84: Preventing Delinquency though Positive Youth Development"
- State of Education RA and Upcoming Legislation-Tape 522-98M (Box 3, Folder 8)
  June. Scripts for governor's news conference; notes
- Prevention of Child Abuse and Neglect through Parent Education-Tapes 405-01A, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  Letter to NYSUT vice president Cortese from State Education Department re public television teleconference; publicity materials
- Workshop and Thank You-Steve Allen-511-93, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  Draft scripts
- Helping Hands-Gloversville-Cookbook, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  Jan. Interview transcript; audio script re augmenting funding for education
- Science Teacher-Blindness-Amsterdam (Box 3, Folder 12)
  Notes re classroom activities to teach awareness of blindness; video production worksheets re science and math teacher shortage
- Education for Democracy-Law Program, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  April. Interview transcript; "Law at Work" conference brochure; permission forms
- Inside Your Schools-NYSUT Scripts-State of Education, 1984-1985 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  Script for Steve Allen narration; video production scripts; list of "Inside Your Schools" (IYS) promotional tapes distributed to Suffolk County locals; list of meeting dates for locals receiving IYS tapes
- Inside Your Schools (IYS) Transitional, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  Letter describing history and distribution of "Inside Your Schools"; list of program's status in metropolitan markets
- Discipline-Tapes 420-01, 420-08, 420-16 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  Video production worksheets; list of assertive statements re classroom behavior
- Metropolitan Life (503-20s), 1984 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  Publications, The Metropolitan Life Survey of the New York State Teacher (conducted by Louis Harris and Associates); The Metropolitan Life Survey of the American Teacher; production worksheets
- Shanker's R.A. Speech, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  Transcript of Al Shanker's speech at Representative Assembly
- Shanker's Speech-Watertown School Boards-Tape 635-98, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  Transcript of Al Shanker's speech to Watertown School Boards re professionalization; video production worksheet
- Shanker's Speech in Watertown (Press Conference), 1986 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  Transcript of Shanker question and answer session; video production worksheets of press conference
- R.A. Tapes 610-01 through 610-22, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  Field footage segment logs for Representative Assembly
- Research and Educational Services R.A. Both Demo Tapes, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  Video edit logs; Local Leaders' Guide to Research and Educational Issues
- New President's Conference Info, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  Program of events for New Local Presidents Conference, with camera directions noted; script for Hobart video introduction to NYSUT Network
- Summer Projects-Intern and Consultant Times and Assignments, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  Assignment sheets
- NYSUT Newsline, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Scripts; telephone bills; notes
- Alex Haley Saratoga/Syracuse Interview Transcripts-Tape 614-91 and 93, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Transcripts of interviews with Alex Haley at Saratoga Springs and Syracuse; poster re Haley on "The Future of Education" at NYSUT Educational Conference; video production worksheet; newspaper clipping
- Jeff Blatnick-State of Education Inside Your Schools, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  Oct. Video production worksheets
- NYSUT Program-Inside Your Schools, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  Script for Steve Allen introduction; video production worksheets
- Jeff Blatnick Story Script, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  Video production worksheets
- State of Education Discipline Notes (Box 3, Folder 30)
  Handwritten video worksheets
- Lamar Alsop Script-Arts in Education Scrapbook, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  Audio script
- NYSUT Human Relations Discipline Workshops (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Handwritten notes; brochure re NYSUT response to discipline issue
- Brian Fitzgerald-U.S. Senate Youth Program, 1983 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Four photographs, including students with Pres. Ronald Reagan; handwritten notes and video production worksheets
- Alex Haley Saratoga Tapes 614-90 through 614-95 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  Transcript of interview at Saratoga Springs; production worksheets
- Child Abduction (Box 3, Folder 35)
  Video production worksheets; press release
- Tuba Christmas-State of Education, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  Dec. Video production worksheets; photographs and negatives
- Tech Fair IV, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Children at Risk Press Conference, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  Transcript
- Imagination Celebration, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Production video worksheets; publication, "Imagination Celebration: Working the Arts" (collection of Children's Arts Festival written submissions); "Imagigrams" workbook; resource directory for arts-in-education workshops presented at NYSUT Regional Education Conference
- Walter Dunn-Effective Teaching Program-520, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  Description of Effective Teaching Program; handwritten production work sheets
- Watertown-Fort Drum Conference-Tape 519-11 through 20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  Transcript of tape 519-11; scripts; production worksheets
- East Islip-What Makes a Good Teacher (Box 4, Folder 5)
  Video production sheets; audio segment scripts
- State of Education-Empire State Institute for the Performing Arts (ESIPA), SRPs-Tape 518-98M, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  May. Scripts for audio segments; transcript of interview with student (tape 520-50); production worksheets; handwritten notes
- Empire State Institute for the Performing Arts (ESIPA)-Inside Your Schools Scripts-Tape 504-99M, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Feb. Final video production sheets by Schnurr and Jackson Associates, Inc., Marketing, Communications
- State of Education-Empire State Institute for the Performing Arts (ESIPA), 1986 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  Feb. Agreement between NYSUT and Hudson Audio Video Enterprises, Inc., for rental equipment; transcript of interviews; draft of introductory script re State University of New York's ESIPA cultural trip to Russia; working production draft of audio segment
- State of Education-Teacher of the Year-Tape 551-98M, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  Jan. Video production sheets; memo
- Cortese/Barell Legislation-Tape 525-10-11, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  Transcript and video production sheets
- Save Our Schools, Save Our Children-Tape 43508R-43501-04, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  Video production worksheets re crisis in schools; segment for Channel 10 News (ABC special)
- In Your Schools-Back to School-Tape 535-99M, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  Sept. Video production worksheets; newspaper clippings re student cable interns
- State of Education Syracuse-Child Care-Tape 535-99M, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  September. Video production worksheets; announcer's script